<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Inimicus amicus an excellent treatise, shewing, how a man may reape profit by his enemy.</title>
            <title>De capienda ex inimicis utilitate. English</title>
            <author>Plutarch.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20053</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110495</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846028</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846028</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10965</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09782)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10965)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 857:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Inimicus amicus an excellent treatise, shewing, how a man may reape profit by his enemy.</title>
                  <title>De capienda ex inimicis utilitate. English</title>
                  <author>Plutarch.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[42] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By V[alentine] S[immes] for Thomas Bushel [, and are to be sold the [sic] great north doore of Paules],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation (different from STC 20052) of: Plutarch. De capienda ex inimicis utilitate.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC; bookseller's address from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁶ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A man may take profit by his enemy.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf bears a printer's mark.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1900.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10965:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10965:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Inimicus Amicus:</hi> AN Excellent Treatiſe, <hi>ſhewing, how a man</hi> may reape profit by <hi>his Enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <q>SVCH AS I MAKE SVCH WILL I TAKE</q>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London by V.S. for Thomas Buſhel. 1601.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10965:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10965:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the right</hi> Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, William Rider, <hi>Lord Maior of the Citie of</hi> London. T. B. wiſheth all health and happines.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, hauing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened (of late) vpon this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, no leſſe pleaſant to be read, then profitable to be practized; and conſidering how vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a part it were, to ſend ſo worthy a worke, vnto the view of the world, both nameleſſe, and frendleſſe; I bethought my ſelfe of ſome <hi>Mecaenas,</hi> that ſhould vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the defence of it againſt the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſtormes of carping Momistes: At laſt, I reſolued vpon your Honour, whom
<pb facs="tcp:10965:3"/>pietie and Iuſtice hath made famous and renowmed amongſt all men. Wherefore I now humbly preſent the ſame vnto your good Lo. to be intertayned, as you ſhall find it worthy. In the meane time, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending both it and my ſelfe vnto your honourable protection, I commit t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your honor to the tuition of the Almighty.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Vnto your Honour moſt humbly deuoted,</hi> T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:10965:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Inimicus Amicus. An excellent Treatiſe,</hi> ſhewing, howe a man may reape profite by his Enemies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Can not but perceiue how that thou (my deareſt <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Pulcher</hi>) haſte made choice of the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing courſe of life that may be; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou doſt affoorde no leſſe profite to the Common-wealth, wherein thou liueſt, then courteſie to thy par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb facs="tcp:10965:4"/>friends, with whom thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeſt. But forſomuch as a Lande may be found voide of all venomous creatures, as men report of the Iland of <hi>Creete,</hi> but hitherto there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any Common-wealth heard of, which was cleane deſtitute of enuie, emulation, and contention, three fruit full nurſing mothers of enmitie: for, if there were no other cauſe, yet euen friendſhip it ſelfe will ſoone intangle vs with many enmities: which <hi>Chilo</hi> the wiſe man conſidering, demaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of one who vaunted, that hee had neuer an enemy, whether withall, he had any one friend. Wherevppon it ſeemeth to mee, that a States man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things which he ſhuld know concerning his enemies, ought not careleſly to giue eare to the ſaying of <hi>Zenophon,</hi> that it belongeth to a wiſe man euen to reape profite by his enemies. Therefore hauing compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed together in a little Treatiſe, that which not long before I had diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:10965:4"/>of, I haue ſent it thee, almoſt word for word as it was vttered, omitting all precepts of Politicall gouernment written by me, as knowing that book of mine to bee ſeldome out of your hands.</p>
            <p>Former Ages thought it ſufficient to keepe themſelues vntouched from the rage of all ſtraunge and wilde beaſts, and this onely was the end of all their combate with them: But in theſe our dayes men hauing at length learned howe to make vſe of them, nowe they doe euen reape manifolde commodities by them, as beeing nouriſhed by their bodies, cloathed by their wooll, medicined by theyr gall, and other entrailes; and laſtly, armed with their skinnes, ſo that nowe wee may iuſtly feare, leſt that through want of wilde beaſts, mans life doe waxe altogether brutiſh, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue, and ſauage: ſith then it ſufficeth ſome, not to bee iniured of their ennemies: but yet others,
<pb facs="tcp:10965:5"/>of the wiſer ſort, it becommeth euen to reape profite by them, as <hi>Zeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon</hi> giueth counſell, wee muſt not therefore be incredulous, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſearch out the Methode and the Arte howe to bee able to attayne to that perfection, very needefull for ſuch who can not liue without ſome ennemies. The husbandman can not frame euery tree according to his minde, nor the hunter tame euery wilde beaſt, yet both haue found meanes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owe, the one, by barren trees, the other, by wilde beaſts, might receiue much profite: Sea water is no leſſe vnſauorie then vnwholeſome, and yet it nouriſheth fiſh, and affoords conuenient paſſage to tranſporte whatſoeuer profitable were. The <hi>Satyre,</hi> at the firſt ſight of fire, woulde needes haue kiſſed and embraced it: but <hi>Prometheus</hi> in the Poet checked him with this verſe:
<pb facs="tcp:10965:5"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Thou hairie goate,</l>
                  <l>from touch of fire abſtaine,</l>
                  <l>Leſt that thy beardleſſe chinne</l>
                  <l>too late complaine.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And yet it giueth light, and yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth heate; yea it is a moſt needefull helpe to the skilfull vſe, in what Art ſoeuer. Let vs likewiſe conſider our ennemy (though otherwiſe hee bee altogether hurtfull and vntractable) whether perchance one may touch him gently, vſe him wiſely, and reape good by hym profitably. There bee many thinges which are greeuous, burthenſome, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the nature of thoſe on whom they light, and yet you ſee how that euen ſickeneſſe it ſelfe giueth ſome good occaſion to liue at eaſe, and howe that much turmoyle befalling to others, hath beene both a ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening, and a practiſe of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience: yea more, euen the loſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:10965:6"/>goodes and baniſhment hath occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned ſome, as, <hi>Diogenes</hi> and <hi>Crates,</hi> to betake themſelues to the ſtudie of of Philoſophie.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Zeno,</hi> when hee heard newes of his ſhipwracke, preſumed to ſay, I thanke thee good Fortune, that thou haſt drouen me to a poore Studients gowne. For euen as the beaſts of the beſt conſtitution, and of good digeſtion, deuoure and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct Serpents and Scorpions, yea, ſome are ſo nouriſhed, through the extreame heate of their ſtomackes, and good temperature of their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, with ſtones and ſhell-fiſhe, whereas weake and queaſie ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes are ready to vomite, with taſting eyther bread or wine: euen ſo doe the vnwiſe ſpoyle friendſhippe it ſelfe, whereas men of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding can make no ſmall vſe, euen by their ennemies.</p>
            <p>Therefore firſt it ſeemeth to mee, that that very thing which is moſt
<pb facs="tcp:10965:6"/>hurtefull in enmitie, may become moſt profitable to men of diſcretions but by what meanes ſhall that come to paſſe you will ſay? For thine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie carefully watching, dooth narrowely obſerue all thy actions, and on euery ſide dooth curiouſly prie into thy life, gaping after euery occaſion of harming, and dooth, not onely as the beaſt <hi>Lynx</hi> by his ſight, pierce through trees, ſtockes, and ſtones, but dooth ſearch out thine actions, and vndermine thine enterpriſes, and that euen by thy ſeruants, friendes, kinsfolkes, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar acquaintaunce: for oftentimes our friendes, through our negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and delay, are ſicke, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen dead before wee are aware of it, whereas through our ouermuch cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitie, wee can hardely forbeare from hearkening euen after the very dreames of our ennemies. But as for thy ſickeneſſe, debts, or domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arres with thy wife, they will
<pb facs="tcp:10965:7"/>be ſooner concealed from thy ſelfe, then from thine ennemie, yea aboue all, hee will purſue thy faultes, and trace after them moſt daungerouſly. And euen as vultures doe followe the ſmell of dead carkaſſes, as not able for to take the ſent of pure and wholeſome bodies, in like manner, the woundes and diſtempered affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions incident in our life, doe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our ennemies. And to theſe come ruſhing our ill-willers, and violently take holde of them, and rip them vp.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is moſt expedient for thee to liue very circumſpectly, to take heede to thy ſelfe, and ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay, nor doe, any thing raſhly, or vnaduiſedly: but rather, to leade thy life, as it were keeping an exact diet, without blame, or reprehenſion whatſoeuer: for this heedefulneſſe ſo repreſſing the paſſion of oure mindes, and keeping Reaſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her boundes of duetie, dooth
<pb facs="tcp:10965:7"/>frame a carefull deſire, and ſettled purpoſe, to liue vprightly and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly: for euen as Citties well taught and tempered with the continuall warres of their next neighbours, do learne good diſcipline, and embrace a good and well ordered gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their common-weale: euen ſo thoſe, which through others en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities are conſtrained to haue aneve to their life, to abſtaine from care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe and negligence, and to doe all things with a kinde of careful dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritie, beeing ledde with cuſtome, themſelues ſcarce perceiuing it, they doe incline to a courſe of life voyde of errour, and doe ſettle their beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and adorne their manners, with very little helpe of learning: for they who haue at hand that verſe of <hi>Homer,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>How then (alas)</l>
                  <l>would Priamking of (Troy,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10965:8"/>And Priams ſonnes</l>
                  <l>be fild with ſcorning ioy.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Are thereby withdrawne and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted from all things which might miniſter to their enemies any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of reioycing or laughter: we ſee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes how that players and muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Theaters, if they be alone by themſelues, do play their parts careleſly, and without alacritie, but being once in ſtrife and emulation, with any others, they do not only endeuour themſelues to excell, but take care to haue their Inſtruments in exceeding good order, to tune them choicely, and to frame their conſort moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd abſolute: euen ſo he t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t knoweth that his enemie is a iealous enuier both of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> life and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>tion, will preſently looke more narrowly to himſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xamine his actions more exactly, and frame his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fe more orderly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of vice, that when w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> offend, we
<pb facs="tcp:10965:8"/>ſtand in awe more of our enemies then of our friends: wherevpon <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſica,</hi> whenas many ſuppoſed and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that the Roman comonweale, was now placed in a ſecure eſtate, whenas both the Carthaginians were vtterly deſtroyed, and the Achaians brought vnder the yoke of bondage, nay rather (quoth he) we are in moſt dangerat this very time, hauing none left vs, whom we might, either feare for danger, or who ſhould keepe vs in awe. And herevnto the ſaying of <hi>Diogenes</hi> no leſſe agreeing to Policie, then Philoſophy, who being asked of one, how he might be auenged of his enemies: why (quoth he) in being a vertuous and honeſt man; if men ſee their enemies horſes or dogges much eſteemed and ſet by, it will mol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt their mindes, and if they chance to ſee their enemies field well tilled, or their garden well proſpering, it cauſeth them to fetch many a deepe ſigh: what then would they doe troweſt
<pb facs="tcp:10965:9"/>thou, if thou ſheweſt thy ſelfe to bee a iuſt, prudent, and honeſt man, in thy words well aduiſed, in thy actions vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted, and in thy diet moſt tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hauing deepe furrowes</l>
               <l>grauen in thy minde,</l>
               <l>From whence each counſell graue</l>
               <l>doth ſpring by kinde</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Poet <hi>Pindarus</hi> ſaith, that men vanquiſhed haue their tongues ſo bound, that they dare not offer to hiſſe, but yet not ſimplie: neither all are ſo, but they chiefly that perceiue themſelues to be ouercome by their enemies, in induſtrie, in goodneſſe, in magnanimitie, in humanitie, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny benefites: theſe be the things (ſaith <hi>Demoſthenes</hi>) which reſtrayne the tongue, which ſeale vp the mouth, which ſtop the breath, and cauſe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:10965:9"/>
               <l>All wicked men in vertue to excell,</l>
               <l>It doth befit a wiſe man very well.</l>
            </q>
            <p>If thou wilt greatly grieue thine enemie, do not accuſe him of his wanton behauiour, of his effeminate minde, of intemperance, of his ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillitie, of his couetouſness but in the meane while, be thou thy ſelfe a man of courage, chaſte, loyall, courteous, and iuſt, amongſt thoſe with whome thou liueſt: but if thou chance to goe ſo farre as to ſpeake ill of him, ſee that thoſe things which to him thou ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteſt, bee far from thine owne ſelfe; ſift and examine thine owne ſoule, ſearch out euery corner therof, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou art faultie, leaſt euen thine own guiltines gall thee, with that verſe of the tragicall Poet.</p>
            <q>
               <l>(To heale all others (foole)</l>
               <l>thou doeſt not ſticke,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10965:10"/>Whenas thy crazie corps</l>
               <l>is weake and ſicke.</l>
            </q>
            <p>If thy enemie terme thee vnlearned, ſtriue to ſhew thy vttermoſt indeuors and dilligence; if fearefull, ſtir vp thy valour and corrage, if laſciuious, wipe cleane out of thy minde, that little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning impreſſion of wantonneſſe ſecretly lurking therein: for there is nothing more ſhamefull, nothing more odious, then a ſlander retorted vpon the aucthor thereof; but euen as the refracted light doth more hurt the weake eye-ſight, euen ſo repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions iuſtly redounding backe, do moſt of all grieue the euill ſpeaker: for as the winde called <hi>Caecias</hi> draweth vnto it clowdes, ſo a vicious life bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all reports: therefore <hi>Plato,</hi> as oft as he kept company with any, who vnſeemly behaued themſelues, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing himſelf in priuate, was wont to ſay to himſelfe: what, am I ſuch a one? ſo he which hath ſlandered an
<pb facs="tcp:10965:10"/>other mans life, if by and by he do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine and well order his owne, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by forming and framing it to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary mould, he ſhal reape ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie by his ſlander, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe both ſeemeth, and is altogether vaine and vnprofitable. It ſeemeth to moſt men moſt rediculous, if a crooke-backe or bald-pate do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche or vpbrayde another with the ſame imperfections; but it deſerueth more then ordinary laughter, if a man do mocke and reproch another with that wherewith he himſelfe may iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be mocked and reproched, like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that which <hi>Leo</hi> Emperour of <hi>By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zantium</hi> aunſwered vnto a certaine crooke-backe, which ieſted at his bleare eyes, ſaying, thou reprocheſt me with defect of nature, and thou carrieſt <hi>Nemeſis</hi> vpon thy backe, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do not thou obiect adultry to an other, thy ſelfe madding after the loue of boyes; nor yet prodigallitie, they ſelfe being a niggard. <hi>Alemaeon</hi> in the
<pb facs="tcp:10965:11"/>Poet checked <hi>Adraſtus</hi> in this ſort.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Thy cruell ſister</l>
               <l>Did her husband ſlay.</l>
            </q>
            <p>What then did <hi>Adraſtus?</hi> he would not caſt in his teeth an other bodies fault, but euen his owne, thus:</p>
            <q>
               <l>But thine owne hand</l>
               <l>Thy mother made away.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So alſo <hi>Domitius</hi> reproching <hi>Craeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> ſaid, didſt not thou weepe for the death of thy Lamprey which thou noriſhedſt in thy pond? wherevpon <hi>Craeſſus</hi> replied, didſt not thou burie three wiues without one teare? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that reprocheth, muſt not be witty in his owne conceit, lowd in his voyce, and lewd in his talke, but rather blameleſſe and faultleſſe in his life: for it ſeemeth that euen God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath to no one ſo much enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this golden precept <hi>(Knowe thy
<pb facs="tcp:10965:11"/>ſelfe)</hi> as vnto him, who is about to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch another; leaſt ſpeaking what hee would, hee heare that which hee would not, for ſuch a one (as <hi>Sophocles</hi> the tragicke Poet tels vs.)</p>
            <q>
               <l>Whoſe willing tongue</l>
               <l>hath fild each iching eare,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwillingly</l>
               <l>like ſlanders needs muſt heare.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Behold now what profit there is in reproching our enemies, and yet there is no leſſe commoditie receiued by being reproched of our enemies. Wherfore <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> ſaid not amiſſe, that thoſe that would liue free from vice, haue neede either of moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained freinds, or of moſt bitter ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, becauſe thoſe by their admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and thoſe by their reproches, do withdraw him from vice, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that now a dayes friendſhip is become feeble in reprehending free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, talkatiue in flattering, and mute in
<pb facs="tcp:10965:12"/>admoniſhing, wee muſt learne the truth, euen of our enemies. For euen as <hi>Telephus,</hi> when among his owne friendes, he found-none to cure his wound, permitted his enemy to doe it: ſo muſt hee that hath not a friend to correct him, ſuffer the reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his enemie, hauing regard rather to the deede it ſelfe, then to the mind of the reprehender: and euen as he who purpoſed to kil <hi>Promethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the <hi>Theſſalian,</hi> opened his impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume with his ſworde, and by that meanes both ſaued his life, and cured him of his diſeaſe: euen ſo very often a taunt, which either anger or enmitie hath caſt vpon vs, doth ſalue ſome wound of our ſoule, either vnknown through ignorance, or vnregarded through negligence: but the moſt part of men conſider not the truth of the reproch obiected, but endeuour rather to find ſome fault in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon reproaching, and ſo, much like wraſtlers, they do not wipe from
<pb facs="tcp:10965:12"/>themſelues the duſt of reproches, but rather beſprinkle others with the ſame; and ſo go grapling with them, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ouerthrowing one another: yea rather he that is noted for ſome crime by his enemies, if it be true, by and by he ought with farre more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to purge it away, then a man would wipe out of his garment any apparant ſpot or blemiſh: but if falſe, then we ought to enquire out the cauſe, which was the cauſe of the fault finding, &amp; withal, he muſt feare, and take good heed, leaſt he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any thing at vnawaies, any way like, or neere to that for which he was reproched; as for example: <hi>Lacides</hi> King of <hi>Argos</hi> was accounted ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what laſciuious, onely for his ſleeke lookes and mincing gate: ſo <hi>Pompey,</hi> albeit, a man farre from all luſt and effeminaties, beecauſe hee vſed to ſcratch his head with one finger: was noted with the ſame crime: ſo <hi>Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſus</hi> was thought to haue abuſed one of
<pb facs="tcp:10965:13"/>the veſtall virgins, by reaſon of a farme which he greatly deſired to buy of her, and for that cauſe, to obtaine his content, he very often conuerſed with her apart: ſo <hi>Poſthumia,</hi> bicauſe ſhe was ſo giuen to laughter, and ſomewhat forward in talking with men, was ſuſpected of her honeſtie, and that ſo farre forth, that ſhe was accuſed thereof openly in the court, but in the end, being found guiltleſſe, and acquited by <hi>Spurius Minutius,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then high prieſt, ſhe had this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueate of him, that hereafter ſhe ſhuld not vſe words vnſutable to her life: ſo <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> by <hi>Pauſanius,</hi> although moſt cleare in himſelf, was ſuſpected of treaſon, as vſing him friendly, and writing &amp; ſending oft to him. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when a falſe thing is obiected, it muſt not be neglected and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as being a lie, but rather we muſt ſearch out, if either we, or any of our friends, haue ſpoken, or done, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted any ſuch things, which
<pb facs="tcp:10965:13"/>might carry ſome likelyhoode of that ſlander, and ſo warily to auoyde it: for if others, by falling into vnexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted miſeries, doe learne their owne good, as <hi>Meropa</hi> in the Poet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth:
<q>
                  <l>Whiles Fortune blinde</l>
                  <l>depriues my hapleſſe eyes</l>
                  <l>Of deerest ioyes,</l>
                  <l>at length ſhe makes me wiſe.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>What dooth hinder vs that wee ſhoulde not accept of a maiſter that taketh no wages, but inſtructeth <hi>gratis,</hi> to wit euen an ennemie, to be profited by him, and learne ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which before wee knewe not: for an enemy dooth perceiue many things farre better than a friend, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a louer (as ſaith <hi>Plato</hi>) is euen blinded with the affection of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon beloued, whereas hatred, beſides curioſitie, hath for his companion, an affected deſire of pratling, whenas one of the enemies of <hi>Hiero</hi> reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:10965:14"/>him with his ſtincking breath: he going home to his wife, queſtioned with her ſharpely, ſaying, What meaneth this, that thou neuer toldſt me of this before? She no leſſe chaſte than harmeleſſe, aunſwered, ſhee thought al men had the ſame ſauour: So that thoſe thinges, which eyther pertayne to the body, or belong to any ſenſe, or elſe bee apparant in all mens ſights, are ſooner knowne by a mans ennemies, than by his friends or familiars. Beſides, it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſo to bridle the tongue (which is not the leaſt parte of Vertue) as, to frame it to be alwayes obedient, and controlde by Reaſon, vnleſſe a man by much practiſe, by great care, and by all earneſt indeuours, doe ſtriue for to ſubdew thoſe rebellious paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the minde, amongſt which Anger beareth not the leaſt ſway: for a worde which vnwittingly dooth breake out of the mouth, as it is in the Poet:
<pb facs="tcp:10965:14"/>
               <q>
                  <l>My deerest childe,</l>
                  <l>what ſpeach ſtrange and vncouth,</l>
                  <l>Hath burst from out</l>
                  <l>the fenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d walles of thy mouth?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>When ſuch wordes (I ſay) flie careleſly out of themſelues, they do as it were, ſlide and ſlippe away moſt commonly from vnexerciſed, and vnſetled mindes: which, when it happeneth, it argueth great weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde, much diſtempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of iudgement, with no leſſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage ſtrangeneſſe of behauiour, in as much as for a mannes ſpeeche, a thing, of it ſelfe, of leaſt account (as wee reade in diuine <hi>Plato</hi>) both by the gods, and by men, a moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous puniſhment is allotted, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſilence is alwayes without daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: neyther onely (as <hi>Hipocrates</hi> ſayeth) dooth it preuent thirſt, but aboue all, being wiſely vſed, when wee are reproached, it preſerueth a kinde of grauitie altogether Socrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,
<pb facs="tcp:10965:15"/>call, or rather Herculean, for <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules,</hi> as it is in the Poet:
<q>
                  <l>—Carde not a flie</l>
                  <l>for all backebiting termes.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Neither ſurely is it more laudable or godly to be quiet at the rebuke of our enemies, and to ſaile careleſly by it, as by a dangerous rocke, but practiſe of our patience is farre more to be affected: For, if thou art once inured to beare patiently a contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious ennemy, thou wilt eaſily ſuffer the rage of thy rayling wife, thou wilt leſſe bee troubled with the bitter checke of thy brother or friend: yea more, thou wilt ſuſtayne euen the ſcourge of thy parents, wythout any commotion of thy minde: for <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> did forbeare <hi>Xantippe</hi> his wife, beeing a very froward and wayward woman, becauſe hee thought hee might better conuerſe with others, if hee were accuſtomed to forbeare with her: but it is much more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to bee able to tollerate calamitie,
<pb facs="tcp:10965:15"/>as being fore-prepared by long exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the opprobrious taunts and reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of our enimies Py this means we make ſhew of our mild diſpoſition, &amp; vnmoued patience, euen towards our enemies: for here is a more vſe of ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, of an high erected ſpirite, and of gentlenes, then euen in friendſhip it ſelfe. For it is not ſo commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to doe well to a mans friend, as it is ſhamefull, not to doe it in time of his neede: ſo that, to let ſlippe the occaſion of reuenging our enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, being offered, argueth much humanitie. But hee that hath a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-feeling compaſſion of his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted enemy, who helpes his neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities who ſheweth mercy to his diſtreſſed children, and vnderprop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his decaying family, whoſoeuer dooth not both loue him for his cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, and praiſe him for his goodnes, that man (as the Poetſaieth)
<q>
                  <l>Sure hath abreast</l>
                  <l>hewne out of Adamant,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:10965:16"/>A man may take profit</l>
                  <l>And heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>amde</l>
                  <l>of peereleſſe Diamant.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Caeſar</hi> commaunded the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne monuments of <hi>Pompey,</hi> to be agayne ſet vp, <hi>Cicero</hi> told him, that in erecting the Trophies of <hi>Pompey,</hi> hee hadde eſtabliſhed his owne. Therefore a man muſt not ſpare to praiſe his very ennemy, and to honour him too, if hee doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it: for the commender is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by more praiſe-woorthy, and better to be beleeued whenſoeuer he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth, as not hating the man, but reproouing the matter: but that which is yet moſt profitable and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, is, that hee, who doth once accuſtome himſelfe to praiſe euen his enemy, and neuer grieues, nor enuies his proſperous ſucceſſe, that man muſt needes be farre eſtranged from grudging and enuying at the proſperitie of his friends and famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and (I pray you) what exerciſe
<pb facs="tcp:10965:16"/>can poſſible woorke ſo much good for our ſoules, or frame our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition better, than that which cleane taketh away that too much affected humor of enuy and emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For euen as in a Citty there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things neceſſary, though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe not ſo good, which being once allowed by cuſtome, and confirmed by force of law, cannot be eaſily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, how pernitious ſoeuer they be; euen ſo, enmitie acompanies, with hatred, with enuie, with a delight in other mens harmes, and with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of receiued iniuries, and yet leaues them all in the minde: beſides all theſe, enters in fraudulent dealing, deepe deceipts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and perfidious trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries, as preſuppoſing theſe things may lawfully be vſed towards our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: &amp; then being ingraffed, they can by no meanes be rooted out with head-ſtrong affections, if we do not
<pb facs="tcp:10965:17"/>curbe them, in conuerſing with our enemies, it is to be feared, leſt being ouercome by cuſtome, we vſe them euen with our friends: if then <hi>Pitha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> did very well, in accuſtoming his Diſciples, euen in vnreaſonable creatures, to abſtaine from crueltie and iniuries, ſo that he would intreat both fowlers and fiſhers, to let go the one his birds, the other his fiſh, being taken; or at the leaſt redeemed them with money and ſo let them looſe; yea &amp; forbade the ſlaughter of any tame heaſt whatſoeuer: much more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous queſtionleſſe were it, if that euen being enemies, in contentions and iarres betweene man and man, wee would ſhew our ſelues to be noble minded, vpright, and true hearted, by controuling, and repreſſing all vile degenerate, and hurtefull paſſions of our minder; to the intent, that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſing with our friends, our patience may be vnmouable and our ſelues ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayning
<pb facs="tcp:10965:17"/>from all maner of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Scaur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was <hi>Domit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> priuate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, and publike accuſer, yet when as before the iudgement day a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſeruaunt of <hi>Domitius</hi> came to <hi>Scaurus,</hi> as being about to tell him ſomwhat againſt his maſter, he would not ſuffer him to ſpeake, but appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending him, ſent him backe to his maſter: ſo likewiſe <hi>Cato</hi> accuſing <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rena</hi> of bribery, in ſuing for offices, and gathering together proofes to confirme his accuſation, in the meane ſeaſon there followed him at his heels (according to the faſhion of thoſe times) certaine men who ſpied out all his proceedings and asked him now and then, whether he purpoſed to do any thing touching the accuſation that day or no, if he had ſaid no, they preſently beleeued it, and went their way: and this ſurely was a ſtrong ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of that great eſtimation which they had of <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o;</hi> and yet it is
<pb facs="tcp:10965:18"/>far more laudable, if being enuied, to deal iuſtly eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with our vtter enemies, we neuer either vniuſtly defraude, or craftely circumuent our friends and acquantance. But ſith that euery larke hath his creſt (according to the ſaying of <hi>Simouides</hi>) ſo euery mans nature is bent to contention, emulation, and enuy, the vnſeperable follower of vayne-minded men (as <hi>Pindarus</hi> ſpeaketh) it were no ſmall profit if a man would poure out ſuch like af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections vpon his enemies, as it were by certaine channels, to driue them farre from our neighbours and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions: which thing <hi>Onomademus</hi> an excellent Stats-man ſeemed to haue throughly conſidered, who in a great tumult which aroſe in the Iland of <hi>Chios,</hi> being one of the ſuperior facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, counſelled his felowes, that they ſhould not expell al their aduerſaries, but ſtill leaue ſome in the Cittie (leaſt ſaid he) otherwiſe being voyd of all
<pb facs="tcp:10965:18"/>our enemies, we ſhould beginne to quarrell with our friends: beſides, theſe humors being ſpent vppon our enemies, they will leſſe greiue our friendes; for the potter needs not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy the potter: (as the Poet <hi>Hoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſaith,) nor the muſitian the muſitian, nor the neighbour be iealous of his neighbour, or kinſman, or brother now beginning to proſper. But if no way may be found, whereby thou maiſt be free from ſtrife, enuy, and contentions, at leaſt frame thy ſelfe, to grieue at the happy ſucceſſe of thine enemies, and ſtir vp that conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious edge, by ſharpening and whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it on thy enemies, for euen as handſome Gardeners, imagine that rootes and violets will proſper the better, being ſet by garlicke and oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, becauſe all that whatſoeuer is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and vnſauory in the noriſhment of the earth, is deriued into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, euen ſo our enemie, drawing to him,
<pb facs="tcp:10965:19"/>ſelfe, and receiuing all our rancor and malice, will make vs more tractable and louing to our friendes in their proſpentie. Therefore we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with our enemies for glory for power, or any lawfull increaſe of our wealth, and not only abſtayne from repining, if they go beyond vs in any thing, but rather obſerue the meanes whereby they haue excelled vs, and endeuor to ſurpaſſe them in induſtry, in conſtancie of labours, and in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance: yea let vs be our enemies iealous obſeruers, in that ſort as <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtocles</hi> was wont to ſay, that <hi>Milti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> victory in <hi>Marathon</hi> bereaued him of his ſleepe: for thoſe which thinke that their enemies do ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe them, either in publike charge, or in pleading, or in gouerning the commonwealth, or els in the fauor of princes, or multitude of friends; thoſe men if they conuert a glorious kinde or practicall emulation into a certaine
<pb facs="tcp:10965:19"/>deiected and baſe-minded repining, they are vexed with an idle and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe enuy, but he that is not blinded with the hatred of his enemie, but as an vncorrupt and vnpartiall ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, doth behold his manners, his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, his doings, he ſhall perceiue that the moſt part of thoſe things which he enuyed in him, were gotten by his dilligent prouidence, and good carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; and thereby ayming at the end, he will increaſe his good deſire of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie and glory, and cutting off each vayne and ſlouthfull affection. But if our enemies, by flattering, by ſubtil dealing, by ſuites in law, by taking of bribes, do get any credit or rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either in court, or common-woule, that ſhall not onely giue vs any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of griefe, but euen gift vs very much, by oppoſing againſt them the liberty of our minde, and the pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es of our life, free from al reproch what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer: for (if we may beleeue <hi>Plato</hi>)
<pb facs="tcp:10965:20"/>what maſſe of gold ſoeuer, is either ouer, or vnder the corth, deſerues not to be compared with vertue, beſides, that ſaying of <hi>Solo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ought ſtill to be in our mouthes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>We ſcorne to change</l>
               <l>For ſtore of worldly wealth,</l>
               <l>Rich vertues meede,</l>
               <l>Our ſoules eternall health.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Much leſſe ſhould we preferre the trencher-hired applauſe of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators in a Theater, or the honours and firſt places amongſt the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuches, Concubines, and great men belonging to princes, before our ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: for nothing deſerues, either ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, or emulation, whoſe being is ſharnefull; But that the louer is euer blinded with affection towards his beloued, (as <hi>Plato</hi> tels vs) and we do with more eaſe perceiue a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full action, when it is committed by
<pb facs="tcp:10965:20"/>our enemies; howſoeuer neither the ioy which we haue by their miſdeeds, nor the griefe which we conceiue of their good deeds, ought to be idle and vnprofitable vnto vs, but rather we ought ſo to frame the matter of both ſides, that both in ſhunning their vices, we wax more abſolute, and in imitating their vertues, we become more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then they themſelues.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:10965:21"/>
            <p>Imprinted at London <hi>by Vat. S. for Thomas</hi> Buſhel, and are to be ſold the great North doore of Paules.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10965:21"/>
               <figure>
                  <q>SVCH AS I MAKE SVCH WILL I TAKE</q>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
